<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Chromatin Compartments and Selection on X</article-title>
<subtitle>How Edges of Active Chromatin Align with Selection Regions in
Primates</subtitle>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Jørgensen</surname>
<given-names>Søren</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Søren Jørgensen</string-name>

<email>201906763@post.au.dk</email>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">201906763@post.au.dk</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>


<abstract>
<p>This is a dummy abstract, dreamt up by chatGPT. This thesis
investigates the 3D chromatin architecture of the X chromosome in
baboons, macaques, and humans, focusing on chromatin compartments during
spermatogenesis. Using publicly available Hi-C data, interaction maps
were created to identify Principal Component 1 (PC1) compartments,
revealing distinct compartmentalization patterns among species. The
analysis included transition zones, where chromatin shifts between
compartment types, and their correlation with positively selected
regions. By comparing these zones with evolutionarily significant
regions, the study explores how chromatin structure influences
evolutionary pressures. Key findings include conserved chromatin
features that may help retain non-advantageous alleles, suggesting a
role for selfish genetic elements in genome evolution. This research
offers new insights into the relationship between chromatin architecture
and evolutionary dynamics across primate species.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Hi-C</kwd>
<kwd>Chromatin Compartments</kwd>
<kwd>Selection</kwd>
</kwd-group>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <sec id="sexual-reproduction-spermatogenesis-meiosis">
    <title>Sexual reproduction (spermatogenesis, meiosis)</title>
    <p>The production of gametes in a sexually reproducing organism is a
    highly complex process that involves numeruous elements.
    Spermatogenesis, the process of forming male gametes, involves four
    stages of differentiation from a germ cell through
    <italic>spermatogonia</italic>, <italic>pachytene
    spermatocyte</italic>, and <italic>round spermatids</italic> to
    <italic>spermatozoa</italic>, or <italic>sperm</italic>
    (<xref alt="Wang et al. 2019" rid="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019" ref-type="bibr">Wang
    et al. 2019</xref>), and it is the very basis of male reproduction.
    The specialized cell division of meiosis neatly handles the pairing,
    recombination, and segregation of homologous chromosomes, thereby
    ensuring proper genetic distribution. Deeply understanding the steps
    of molecular steps of reproduction and how our genetic material is
    inherited is essential in biology, bringing insight to areas such as
    speciation, population diversity, and (male) infertility.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="selfish-genes-and-randomness">
    <title>Selfish genes (and randomness)</title>
    <p>The conventional story of meiosis in gametogenesis is one of
    random segregation of the sex chromosomes. They split into haploid
    gametes, where each chromosome has an equal chance of being passed
    on to a gamete. That seems like a fair game, but what if some genes
    are cheating the system by making others less viable. A meiotic
    driver is a selfish gene element that modulates meiosis and
    preferentially transmits its own allele through meiosis, regardless
    of the downstream fitness effects it may have (good or bad) on the
    organism it is part of. This phenomenon challenges the traditional
    understanding of selection, extending its scope beyond the fitness
    effects on an organism to include selective pressures at the
    molecular level. For example, if some genes on the X chromosome
    create a disadvantage for gametes that <italic>do not</italic>
    contain those genes, making sure the Y chromosome is not as viable
    as the X, resulting in a sex imbalance and possibly numerous other
    downstream effects. That is exactly what is coined <italic>sex
    chromosome meiotic drive</italic>
    (<xref alt="Jaenike 2001" rid="ref-jaenike_sex_2001" ref-type="bibr">Jaenike
    2001</xref>), a result of selfish genetic elements.</p>
    <p>Motivated by previous results in the Munch Research group
    (<xref alt="Munch 2024" rid="ref-munch_group_2024" ref-type="bibr">Munch
    2024</xref>) on hybrid incompatibility and extended common
    haplotypes
    (<xref alt="Skov et al. 2023" rid="ref-skov_extraordinary_2023" ref-type="bibr">Skov
    et al. 2023</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sørensen et al. 2023" rid="ref-sorensen_genome_wide_2023" ref-type="bibr">Sørensen
    et al. 2023</xref>) that could be explained by meiotic drive, we
    wanted to investigate how these patterns correlate with chromatin
    compartments.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="high-throughput-chromosome-conformation-capture-hi-c">
    <title>High-Throughput Chromosome Conformation Capture
    (Hi-C)</title>
    <p>Our DNA can be divided into different orders of structure.
    <italic>3C</italic> focus on identifying the highest orders of
    organization inside the nucleus, that is, when the 30 nm thick coil
    of chromatin fibers folds into loops, Topologically Associating
    Domains (TADs), and chromatin compartments. Here, we narrow our
    focus on the largest of the structures,
    <italic>compartments</italic>, that is known to determine
    availability to transcription factors, thus making an
    <italic>A</italic> compartment <italic>active</italic>—and the
    <italic>B</italic> compartment <italic>inactive</italic>. The
    introduction of the Hi-C (high-throughput 3C) method
    (<xref alt="Lieberman-Aiden et al. 2009" rid="ref-lieberman_aiden_comprehensive_2009" ref-type="bibr">Lieberman-Aiden
    et al. 2009</xref>) opened new possibilities for exploring the
    three-dimensional organization of the genome.</p>
    <p></p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="methods">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>In this project, we formulate two objectives:</p>
  <p><bold>A</bold>: Reproduce the Hi-C interaction maps and
  eigendecomposition from
  (<xref alt="Wang et al. 2019" rid="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019" ref-type="bibr">Wang
  et al. 2019</xref>), with some modifications. We briefly use
  <italic>HiCExplorer</italic>, but change the analyses to use the
  <italic>Open2C Ecosystem</italic>
  (<xref alt="Open Chromosome Collective 2024" rid="ref-open2c" ref-type="bibr">Open
  Chromosome Collective 2024</xref>) which have a Pyton API as well as
  command-line functions, which can be paired very well with Jupyter
  Notebooks. The majority of the data analysis was run with a
  <italic>gwf</italic> workflow, and the commands that were visually
  inspected were run in Jupyter Notebooks.</p>
  <p><bold>B</bold> Compare with regions of selection that are found in
  <italic>papio anubis</italic>, and maybe in <italic>human</italic>
  too. Investigate the biological meaning of the results.</p>
  <p>All computations were performed on GenomeDK (GDK) [ref], an HPC
  cluster located on Aarhus Uninversity, and most of the processing of
  the data was nested into a <italic>gwf</italic> workflow [ref], a
  workflow manager developed at GDK. I would like to thank GDK and
  Aarhus University for providing computational resources and support
  that contributed to these research results.</p>
  <p>The whole of this project is carried out with reproducibility in
  mind, so an effort (and quite a significant amount of time) has been
  put into documenting code and organizing the project for readbility
  and transparency through a Quarto project [ref]. Therefore, all code,
  virtual environments and text is made available as a Quarto book,
  rendered directly from the GitHub repository with GitHub Pages []. To
  make this possible, the Quarto documentation has been extensively
  studied and discussed with <italic>KMT</italic> [ref, aknowledge].</p>
  <sec id="downloading-data-and-project-structure">
    <title>Downloading Data and Project Structure</title>
    <p>To reproduce the results from
    (<xref alt="Wang et al. 2019" rid="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019" ref-type="bibr">Wang
    et al. 2019</xref>), I chose to use their raw data directly from the
    SRA portal [ref]. I filtered the data to contain all their
    paired-end Hi-C reads, and included only macaque samples. The data
    set also contains RNAseq data, and the same tissues for both macaque
    and mouse. The meta data for the data set was extracted into a
    runtable <monospace>SRA-runtable.tsv</monospace>. To get an overview
    of the data accessions used in this analysis, we will first
    summarize the runtable that contains the accession numbers and some
    metadata for each sample
    (<xref alt="Table 1" rid="tbl-runtable-summary">Table 1</xref>). It
    adds up to ~1Tb of compressed <monospace>fastq</monospace> files,
    holding ~9.5 billion reads, roughly evenly spread on the 5 tissue
    types.</p>
    <fig id="tbl-runtable-summary">
      <caption><p>Table 1: Summary of the data accessions used in this
      analysis</p></caption>
      <table-wrap>
        <table id="T_55add">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th> </th>
              <th id="T_55add_level0_col0">source_name</th>
              <th id="T_55add_level0_col1">GB</th>
              <th id="T_55add_level0_col2">Bases</th>
              <th id="T_55add_level0_col3">Reads</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td id="T_55add_level0_row0">0</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row0_col0">fibroblast</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row0_col1">211.403275</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row0_col2">553,968,406,500</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row0_col3">1,846,561,355</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td id="T_55add_level0_row1">1</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row1_col0">pachytene spermatocyte</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row1_col1">274.835160</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row1_col2">715,656,614,700</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row1_col3">2,385,522,049</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td id="T_55add_level0_row2">2</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row2_col0">round spermatid</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row2_col1">243.128044</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row2_col2">655,938,457,200</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row2_col3">2,186,461,524</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td id="T_55add_level0_row3">3</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row3_col0">sperm</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row3_col1">164.131640</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row3_col2">428,913,635,400</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row3_col3">1,429,712,118</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td id="T_55add_level0_row4">4</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row4_col0">spermatogonia</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row4_col1">192.794420</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row4_col2">518,665,980,300</td>
              <td id="T_55add_row4_col3">1,728,886,601</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec id="handling-coolers-or-preparing-coolers">
    <title>Handling coolers (Or: preparing coolers)</title>
    <fig id="fig-flowchart-handling-coolers">
      <caption><p>Figure 1: A flowchart showing the pipeline from
      <monospace>.fastq</monospace> to <monospace>.mcool</monospace>.
      The first 6 steps were done with a Probably BioRender or
      Inkscape.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="illustrations/placeholder2000x360.png" />
    </fig>
    <sec id="the-gwf-workflow-targets">
      <title>The <italic>gwf</italic> workflow targets</title>
      <p>A <italic>gwf</italic> workflow was created to handle the first
      part of the data processing, and each accesion number (read pair,
      mate pair) from the Hi-C sequencing was processed in parallel, so
      their execution was independent from each other.</p>
      <sec id="downloading-the-reads">
        <title>Downloading the reads</title>
        <p>The reads were downloaded from NCBI SRA portal [ref] directly
        to GDK using <monospace>sra-downloader</monospace> [ref] through
        docker [ref] as <monospace>.fastq.gz</monospace> files.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="handling-the-reference">
        <title>Handling the reference</title>
        <p>The latest reference genome for rhesus macaque
        (<italic>macaca mulata</italic>), <italic>rheMac10</italic> (or
        <italic>Mmul_10</italic>, UCSC or NCBI naming conventions,
        respectively) was downloaded to GDK from UCSC web servers with
        <monospace>wget</monospace> [ref]. To use
        <monospace>bwa</monospace> (Burrow Wheeler’s Aligner) [ref] for
        mapping, rheMac10 needs to be indexed with both
        <monospace>bwa index</monospace> with the
        <monospace>--bwtsw</monospace> option and
        <monospace>samtools faidx</monospace>, which results in six
        indexing files for <monospace>bwa mem</monospace> to use.</p>
        <p>Needs:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Wang et al. used <italic>rheMac2</italic>, the first
            assembly of rhesus</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Bowtie2 indexing</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="mapping-paired-end-reads">
        <title>Mapping paired-end reads</title>
        <p>Needs:</p>
        <p><bold>HiCExplorer</bold> Initially, recommendations from
        HiCExplorer were used. According to their documentation [ref] it
        is crucial to 1) align reads locally, as Hi-C has a higher
        fraction of reads that are chimeric, and 2) mapping mates
        separately to mitigate some of the heuristics made by aligners
        for standard paired-end libraries. However, the resulting files
        were incompatible with the <italic>open2C</italic> ecosystem,
        and I therefore followed <italic>HiCExplorer</italic> pipeline
        to plot and explore the matrices created from this mapping.
        However, the work was laborious for experimentation, as the
        provided functions all write plots to files. I did not manage to
        make an efficient implementation for plotting the
        <monospace>.h5</monospace> files produced by the pipeline, and I
        relatively quickly shifted to <italic>Open2C</italic> for their
        promises of the greener grass.</p>
        <p>It was not feasible to follow the same approach as Wang et
        al.
        (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
        with both <italic>HiCExplorer</italic> and
        <italic>Open2C</italic>, as they use a third software,
        <italic>HiC-Pro</italic>. Hic-Pro uses bowtie2 in end-to-end
        mode, followed by remapping of 5’-ends of the unmapped reads to
        rescue chimeric fragments along with other mitigations. I argue
        that even though we are trying to reproduce results, it is
        nonsensical to use methods that are not state-of-the-art. That
        said, either widely used method should produce similar
        results.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Bowtie2 (local and end-to-end)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Open2C formats and <monospace>bwa</monospace></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pair-and-sort-the-reads">
        <title>Pair and sort the reads</title>
        <p>Needs:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>mapping mates separately vs. as paired-end reads</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><monospace>pairtools parse</monospace> and
            <monospace>pairtools sort</monospace></p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>discuss the use of default parameters:
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pairtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/protocols_pipelines.html#recommended-pairtools-parameters-for-standard-hi-c-protocols">docs</ext-link></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="filter-deduplicate-pairs">
        <title>Filter (deduplicate) pairs</title>
        <p>At this point we will remove all reads that are mapped to an
        unplaced scaffold. Even though the publication of
        <italic>rhemac10</italic> assembly states they have closed gaps
        between 99% of the contigs since <italic>rhemac8</italic>,
        <italic>rheMac10</italic> still contain more than 2,500 unplaced
        contigs, which are all uninformative when calculating the
        chromatin compartments as is the goal of this analysis.
        Therefore, we simply only include the list of conventional
        chromosomes (1..22, X, Y) when doing the deduplication.
        Initially, the default values were used to remove duplicates,
        where pairs with both sides mapped within 3 base pairs from each
        other are considered duplicates.</p>
        <p><monospace>cooler</monospace> recommend to store the most
        comprehensive and unfilteres list of pairs, and then applying a
        filter on it on the fly by piping from
        <monospace>pairtools select</monospace> I have missed this step,
        so I have not filtered for mapping quality. I will make a
        histogram showing the distribution of mapq scores to see the
        significance of this. Or just rerun that part of the
        analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="create-interaction-matrices-coolers">
        <title>Create interaction matrices (coolers)</title>
        <p>The final part of the <italic>gwf</italic> workflow takes
        <monospace>.pairs</monospace> as input and outputs a
        <monospace>.cool</monospace> file (<italic>cooler</italic>).
        Initially, we read directly from the newly generated
        deduplicated pairs without additional filtering, but here, the
        official recommendation is to filter out everything below
        <inline-formula><alternatives>
        <tex-math><![CDATA[mapq = 30]]></tex-math>
        <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
        by piping the pairs through
        <monospace>pairtools select &quot;(mapq1&gt;=30) and (mapq2&gt;=30)&quot;</monospace>
        to <monospace>cooler cload pairs</monospace>.</p>
        <p>We should have plenty of data to do the filtering, but I
        argue it is not strictly necessary. I will show a histogram of
        the <italic>mapq</italic> scores to convince you [ref].
        Otherwise, I will have fixed this issue.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="notebook-edits">
      <title>Notebook edits</title>
      <p>As <monospace>cooler</monospace> and
      <monospace>cooltools</monospace> have a Python API, the more
      experimental parts of the analysis were moved to Jupyter Notebooks
      (still running on GenomeDK). <monospace>cooltools</monospace>
      comes with a helper library for operations on genomic intervals
      called <monospace>bioframe</monospace>.</p>
      <sec id="pooling-samples-merging-coolers">
        <title>Pooling samples (Merging coolers)</title>
        <p>The samples are grouped into <italic>replicates</italic> with
        a unique <bold>BioSample</bold> ID, but we chose to pool all the
        interaction matrices for each cell type. We argue that when Wang
        et al.
        (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
        determine compartments to be highly reproducible between
        replicates, by merging the replicates we can get a more robust
        signal.</p>
        <p><monospace>cooler merge</monospace> was used to merge all
        samples in each sub-folder (cell type) to just one interaction
        matrix for each cell type. The function merges matrices of the
        same dimensions by simply adding the interaction frequencies of
        each genomic position together, resulting in less empty
        positions by chance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="create-multi-resolution-coolers-zoomify">
        <title>Create multi-resolution coolers (zoomify)</title>
        <p>A feature of working inside the ecosystem of
        <italic>Open2C</italic> [ref] is that it natively provides
        support for storing sparse interaction matrices in multiple
        resolutions in the same file by adding groups to the cooler
        [ref]. We can then efficiently store resolutions (i.e.,
        different bin sizes) that is multiples of the smallest bin size.
        We chose to use 10kb, 50kb, 100kb, and 500kb bins, and the
        resolutions are made by recursively binning the base resolution.
        We call this process zoomifying.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="matrix-balancing-iterative-correction">
        <title>Matrix balancing (Iterative correction)</title>
        <p>Finally, we balance the matrices using the cooler CLI. We use
        <monospace>cooler balance</monospace> with the default options
        which iteratively balances the matrix (Iterative Correction). It
        is first described as a method for bias correction of Hi-C
        matrices in
        (<xref alt="Imakaev et al. 2012" rid="ref-imakaev_iterative_2012" ref-type="bibr">Imakaev
        et al. 2012</xref>), where it is paired with eigenvector
        decomposition, coining the combined analysis <bold>ICE</bold>.
        Here, the eigenvector decomposition of the obtained maps is
        experimentally validated to provide insights into local
        chromatin states.</p>
        <p>[According to <monospace>cooler</monospace> documentation] We
        have to balance the matrices on each resolution, and thus it
        cannot be done prior to zoomifying. They state that the
        balancing weights are resolution-specific and will no longer
        retain its biological meaning when binned with other weights.
        Therefore, we apply <monospace>cooler balance</monospace> to
        each resolution separately.
        <monospace>cooler balance</monospace> will create a new column
        in the <monospace>bins</monospace> group of each cooler ,
        <monospace>weight</monospace>, which can then be included or not
        in the downstream analysis. This means we will have access to
        both the balanced and the unbalanced matrix.</p>
        <p>The default mode uses genome-wide data to calculate the
        weights for each bin. It would maybe be more suitable to
        calculate the weights for <italic>cis</italic> contacts only,
        and that is possible through the
        <monospace>--cis-only</monospace> flag, and that can be added to
        another column, so that we can compare the difference between
        the two methods easily. However, we will only use the default
        mode for now.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eigendecomposition">
        <title>Eigendecomposition</title>
        <p>The eigendecomposition of a Hi-C interaction matrix is
        performed in multiple steps. As value of the eigenvector is only
        <italic>significant</italic> up to a sign, it is convention
        [ref] to use GC content as a phasing track to orient the vector.
        E1 is arbitrarily defined to be positively correlated with GC
        content, meaning a positive E1 value signifies an active
        chromatin state, which we denote a A-type compartment (or simply
        A-compartment). We performed eigendecomposition of two
        resolutions, 100 Kbp and 500 Kbp.</p>
        <p>First, we calculate the GC content of each bin of the
        reference genome, <italic>rheMac10</italic>, which is binned to
        the resolution of the Hi-C matrix we are handling. It is done
        with <monospace>bioframe.frac_gc</monospace>
        (<italic>Open2C</italic>). To calculate the E1 compartments, we
        use only within-chromosome contacts (<italic>cis</italic>), as
        we are not interested in the genome-wide contacts.
        <monospace>cooltools.eigs_cis</monospace> will decorrelate the
        contact-frequency by distance before performing the
        eigendecomposition. <monospace>eigs_cis</monospace> needs a
        <italic>viewframe</italic> (view) to calculate E1 values, the
        simplest view being the full chromosome. However, when there is
        more variance between chromosome arms than within arms, the sign
        of the first eigenvector will be determined largely by the
        chromosome arm it sits on, and not by the chromatin
        compartments. To mitigate this, we apply a
        chromosome-arm-partitioned view of the chromosome (as a bedlike
        format, described in <monospace>bioframe</monospace> docs
        [ref]).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="plotting">
        <title>Plotting</title>
        <p>Needs:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>HiCExplorer: plot with CLI, writes to pngs</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>cooler: plot through python API (fetch matrix from
            cooler)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="results">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Here are the glorious results</p>
  <p></p>
</sec>
<sec id="discussion">
  <title>Discussion</title>
  <p>Here is the discussion</p>
  <p></p>
</sec>
<sec id="bibliography">
  <title>Bibliography</title>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-lieberman_aiden_comprehensive_2009">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Lieberman-Aiden</surname><given-names>Erez</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>Nynke L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Imakaev</surname><given-names>Maxim</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ragoczy</surname><given-names>Tobias</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Telling</surname><given-names>Agnes</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>Ido</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lajoie</surname><given-names>Bryan R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names>Peter J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Dorschner</surname><given-names>Michael O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Groudine</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gnirke</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Stamatoyannopoulos</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mirny</surname><given-names>Leonid A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>Eric S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>Job</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Comprehensive Mapping of Long-Range Interactions Reveals Folding Principles of the Human Genome</article-title>
      <source>Science</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2009-10">2009</year><month>10</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-08-29">2024</year><month>08</month><day>29</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>326</volume>
      <issue>5950</issue>
      <issn>0036-8075, 1095-9203</issn>
      <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.1181369</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1181369</pub-id>
      <fpage>289</fpage>
      <lpage>293</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wang_reprogramming_2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hanben</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Zhenhai</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Suixing</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Dongdong</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Mei</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Yanchao</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Lufan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Yuying</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Qiujun</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Qinghua</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Reprogramming of Meiotic Chromatin Architecture during Spermatogenesis</article-title>
      <source>Molecular Cell</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-02">2019</year><month>02</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-08-29">2024</year><month>08</month><day>29</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>73</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>10972765</issn>
      <uri>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1097276518309894</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2018.11.019</pub-id>
      <fpage>547</fpage>
      <lpage>561.e6</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-skov_extraordinary_2023">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>Laurits</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Coll Macià</surname><given-names>Moisès</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lucotte</surname><given-names>Elise Anne</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cavassim</surname><given-names>Maria Izabel Alves</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Schierup</surname><given-names>Mikkel Heide</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>Kasper</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Extraordinary selection on the human X chromosome associated with archaic admixture</article-title>
      <source>Cell Genomics</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023-03">2023</year><month>03</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-08-30">2024</year><month>08</month><day>30</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>2666979X</issn>
      <uri>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2666979X23000344</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xgen.2023.100274</pub-id>
      <fpage>100274</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-imakaev_iterative_2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Imakaev</surname><given-names>Maxim</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fudenberg</surname><given-names>Geoffrey</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>McCord</surname><given-names>Rachel Patton</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Naumova</surname><given-names>Natalia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Goloborodko</surname><given-names>Anton</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lajoie</surname><given-names>Bryan R</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>Job</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mirny</surname><given-names>Leonid A</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Iterative correction of Hi-C data reveals hallmarks of chromosome organization</article-title>
      <source>Nature Methods</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-10">2012</year><month>10</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-11-08">2024</year><month>11</month><day>08</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <issn>1548-7091, 1548-7105</issn>
      <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/nmeth.2148</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2148</pub-id>
      <fpage>999</fpage>
      <lpage>1003</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-open2c">
    <element-citation>
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Open Chromosome Collective</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Open Chromosome Collective (Open2C)</article-title>
      <source>Open2C</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024-11-13">2024</year><month>11</month><day>13</day>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-11-13">2024</year><month>11</month><day>13</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>https://open2c.github.io/</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-jaenike_sex_2001">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Jaenike</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Sex Chromosome Meiotic Drive</article-title>
      <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2001-11">2001</year><month>11</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-11-14">2024</year><month>11</month><day>14</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>32</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <issn>0066-4162</issn>
      <uri>https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.32.081501.113958</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.32.081501.113958</pub-id>
      <fpage>25</fpage>
      <lpage>49</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-munch_group_2024">
    <element-citation>
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>Kasper</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Munch-group</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024-11">2024</year><month>11</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-11-15">2024</year><month>11</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>https://munch-group.org/research.html</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-sorensen_genome_wide_2023">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Sørensen</surname><given-names>Erik F.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>R. Alan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Liye</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Raveendran</surname><given-names>Muthuswamy</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kuderna</surname><given-names>Lukas F. K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>Jerilyn A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Storer</surname><given-names>Jessica M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kuhlwilm</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fontsere</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>Lakshmi</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bergey</surname><given-names>Christina M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Burrell</surname><given-names>Andrew S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>Juraj</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Phillips-Conroy</surname><given-names>Jane E.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>Fekadu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>Kenneth L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chuma</surname><given-names>Idrissa S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Keyyu</surname><given-names>Julius D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gingras</surname><given-names>Marie-Claude</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>Sejal</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Doddapaneni</surname><given-names>Harshavardhan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Schierup</surname><given-names>Mikkel H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Batzer</surname><given-names>Mark A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>Clifford J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Knauf</surname><given-names>Sascha</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zinner</surname><given-names>Dietmar</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Farh</surname><given-names>Kyle K.-H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Marques-Bonet</surname><given-names>Tomas</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>Kasper</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>Jeffrey</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Genome-wide coancestry reveals details of ancient and recent male-driven reticulation in baboons</article-title>
      <source>Science</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023-06">2023</year><month>06</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-11-15">2024</year><month>11</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>380</volume>
      <issue>6648</issue>
      <issn>0036-8075, 1095-9203</issn>
      <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abn8153</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abn8153</pub-id>
      <fpage>eabn8153</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>

<sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-2-nb-1">
<front-stub>
</front-stub>

<body>
<sec id="supplementary-material-nb-1">
  <title>Supplementary material</title>
  <p>Here is appended the supplementary material</p>
</sec>
</body>



<back>
</back>


</sub-article>

</article>